Guide to the Philip Whalen Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Philip Whalen Papers,
1941-1979.
Whalen, Philip.
8.34 linear ft. (20 document boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1328
4079463
Papers of Philip Whalen, American poet, novelist, and Zen Buddhist associated with the Beat Generation and the San Francisco Renaissance.
Biographical Note
Philip Whalen was born in Portland, Oregon in 1923 and grew up in The Dalles-- a small town in Oregon on the Columbia River. Whalen wrote his first poems while a high school student in The Dalles, but he began to write more seriously and identify himself as a poet while serving in the Air Force during World War II. His position training radio operators left him with ample down time in which to read and to write poetry. After the war ended, Whalen intended to pursue his interests in Asian literature and languages at the University of California at Berkeley, but his economic circumstances required moving back to his family's home in Portland. Back in Portland, Whalen attended Reed College on the GI Bill where he studied English and creative writing, and learned calligraphy from Lloyd Reynolds, a professor of art history and creative writing. It was also at Reed that Whalen met and befriended two other young poets, Lew Welch and Gary Snyder. The three lived together in a Portland rooming house and shared an affinity for the poems of William Carlos Williams and the rhythmic prose of Gertrude Stein. Though they never considered themselves part of an artistic or poetic movement, the three young poets would become core members of the Beat Generation and usher in a new style of West Coast poetry known as the San Francisco Renaissance.
Though Whalen had been studying and writing poetry throughout college and for several years after graduating from Reed he published infrequently during the first few years of his career and was known mostly among other poets in San Francisco and the Pacific Northwest. It wasn't until his participation in the historic 1955 Six Gallery reading that he received national attention. The reading was organized to highlight the work being done by local San Francisco poets and was a major factor in bringing contemporary poetry, especially the work of the Beat poets, into the national cultural consciousness. The event, which was organized by Allen Ginsberg and hosted by Kenneth Rexroth, featured Whalen, Gary Snyder, Michael McClure and Philip Lamantia as well as Ginsberg, who read Howl for the first time at the event.
Whalen's fame grew after the Six Gallery reading and he sold several poems to significant literary journals such as the Evergreen Review before the publication of two major book of poems in 1960, Memoirs of an Interglacial Age and Like I Say. The momentum around the west coast beats that started picking up after the Six Gallery reading continued and became codified with the publication of Don Allen's anthology The New American Poetry, 1945-1960 by the Grove Press. This anthology featured a number of emerging poets and served as a virtual who's who of contemporary poetry, including Whalen, who contributed several poems to the volume. Whalen continued to publish regularly collections of poetry such as On Bear's Head: Selected Poems, Severance Pay: Poems 1967-1969, The Kindness of Strangers: Poems, 1969-1974 through the 1990s. He also wrote three novels- a loose trilogy comprised of Imaginary Speeches for a Brazen Head, You Didn't Even Try, and The Diamond Noodle.
In addition to being a poet, Whalen was also a devout Buddhist. He studied meditative practices and lived in Kyoto Japan in 1966 and 1967 writing immersing himself in Zen Buddhist practices. He was ordained at Zen Buddist priest in 1973 and rechristened Zenshin Ryufu, which means "Zen-mind-dragon-wind." He spent most of the later years of his life living in Zen Centers and monasteries, including a role as the abbot of a monastery in Santa Fe, New Mexico and at the Hartford Street Zen Center in San Francisco where he acted as abbot for the center and its associated AIDS hospice. He retired from his work as an active priest in 1996, but continued to write and publish poetry throughout the 1990s.
Philip Whalen died June 26, 2006.
Scope and Content
The Philip Whalen papers consist of correspondence, manuscripts of Whalen's poetry and prose (both published and unpublished), as well as a small number of publications and publishers' catalogs collected by Whalen.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in 3 series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1962-1972
Series II: Poems and Manuscripts, 1941-1971
Series III: Publications and Documents, 1946-1972
Subjects
Berrigan, Ted.; Brown, William D., 1918-; Di Prima, Diane.; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997.; McClure, Michael.; Malanga, Gerard.; Rexroth, Kenneth, 1905-1982.; Rosenthal, Irving.; Snyder, Gary.; Whalen, Philip.; American literature--20th century.; American poetry--20th century.; Beat generation.; Poems.; Poets, American.; Authors, American.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
M-59 Purchase
Selected Related Material
Philip Whalen Papers at the University of California Berkeley's Bancroft Library.
- Series I: Correspondence,1962-1979
  - Abbott, Keith to Whalen, March- December, 1971 (2 letters) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Abbott, Ward to Whalen, 1968 May 28 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Allen, Tony to Whalen,undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Allen, Donald to Whalen
    - 1963-1966 (3 letters) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1967 January- September (8 letters) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1968 November (2 letters) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1969 September- December (4 letters) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1970 (6 letters) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1971 January- March, (6 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1972-1973, (6 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters to Whalen, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - American Civil Liberties Union of Northern California, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Artisjus, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Aston, James to Whalen, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - B., Wallace to Whalen,undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Baldwin, Geoffrey Rowan to Whalen, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Barrett, Neil to Whalen, 1967 (3 letters) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Baynard, Ed to Whalen, [1968] (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Benedikt, Michael to Whalen, 1974 January 4 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Benello, George to Whalen, John Armstrong, and Gary Snyder, 1965 March 31 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Berkson, Bill to Whalen, 1969 February 3 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Berrigan, Alice Notley,1972-1973 (2 letters) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Berrigan, Ted and Alice Notley to Whalen, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Berrigan, Ted to Whalen,1967-1968, (2 letters) (Box 1, Folder 24)
    (includes draft of poem "Poem for Philip Whalen")
  - Bertolino, James to Whalen, 1968 and undated, (2 letters) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Boucher, Paul to Whalen, 1968 August 29 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Brainard, Joe to Whalen, 1971 July -1972 April(6 letters) (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Brinkman, Rolf Dieter, 1968 (2 letters) (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Brody, Jim to Whalen, 1968, (2 letters) (Box 1, Folder 29)
    (includes poem "War Poems Notation")
  - Brown, William to Whalen,1964-1974 (9 letters) (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Brown, Zoe to Whalen,1966-1967 (3 letters) (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Brownstein, Michael to Whalen, 1972 April 13 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Burke, Clifford to Whalen, December 18, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    (includes poem "Quiet Return to San Francisco, Thanksgiving, 1970")
  - Caen, Herb to Whalen, Gary Snyder, and John Armstrong, 1965 March 23 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Callahan, Bob to Whalen, 1973 May 30 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    (contains a Turtle Island Foundation catalog)
  - Carey, Steve to Whalen,1966-1967 (2 letters) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    (contains "I Will not Faint in the Market" and "Philip Whalen we Love you Come Home")
  - Carpenter, Dan to Whalen
    - 1966 andundated (10 letters) (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 1967 (19 letters) (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1969 (8 letters) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Carrell, Paul to Whalen, 1972 November 23 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Caufle, Don to Whalen, 1968 August 11-12 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Clark, Tom to Whalen
    - 1966 (4 letters) (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 1967 (4 letters) (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 1969 (6 letters) (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 1969 October 26 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      (includes poem "Things About You")
    - 1971 September 16 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Clements, Marshall to Whalen
    - 1968 (3 letters) (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - 1970 July 27 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Committee on Poetry Statements on LeRoi Jones and Lenny Bruce,1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Contemporary Films, 1968 May 8 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Coolidge, Clark to Whalen
    - Undated (5 letters) (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - 1966-1973 (7 letters) (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Corman, Cid to Whalen
    - 1967-1969 andundated (10 letters) (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - 1970-1973 (19 letters) (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Corso, Gregory to Whalen, 1972 December 18 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Conze, Edward to Whalen, 1967 September 22 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Creeley, Robert to Whalen, 1967 November 23 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - DaBoll, Irene and Ray to Whalen, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Danchick, Anita M. Benton to Whalen, 1968 November 5 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Deemer, Bill to Whalen, 1966 andundated (7 letters) (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Denney, Randy to Whalen, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Detro, Gene to Whalen, 1974 July 21 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Dias, Robert Vas to Whalen, 1969 August 6 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Dilia to Whalen, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - DiPrima, Diane to Whalen,1966-1972 (12 letters) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Di Suvero, Victor M. to Whalen, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Dorfman, Elsa to Whalen, 1968 April 28 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Doss, Margot, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Drake, Albert to Whalen, 1971 (2 letters) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Duerden, Richard to Whalen,1966-1970 (6 letters) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Eckert, George, 1968 July 17 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Eigner, Larry to William Brown,undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Eshleman, Clayton to Whalen, 1971 December 18 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Eutsler, Lee to Whalen, 1968 January 28 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Factor, Don to Whalen, 1961 March 19 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Fagin, Larry to Whalen1970-1973 (12 letters) (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Fairbank, Alfred to Whalen, 1966 August 17 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Ferlinghetti, Lawrence to Whalen,1971-1973 (3 letters) (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Finch, Peter to Whalen,1971-1972 (5 letters) (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Friedman, Richard to Whalen, 1973 March 24 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Gay, Rginald to Whalen,undated (3 letters) (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Gifford, Barry to Whalen, 1969 October 24 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Gilbert, Steve to Whalen, June-August, 1968 (2 letters) (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Ginsberg, Allen to Whalen
    - 1966-1968 (18 letters) (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - 1969-1971 (13 letters) (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - 1972-1973 (12 letters) (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - 1974-1979 (11 letters) (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Ginsberg, Louis to Whalen,1968-1971 (4 letters and miscellaneous items) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Gitin, David to Whalen,1968-1970 (5 letters) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Green, Paul to Whalen, 1967 (2 letters) (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Greenfelder, Robert to Whalen, 1965 March 28 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Grossman, Martin to Whalen, 1972andundated, (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Grossman Publishers, 1973 January-June (3 letters) (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Guggenheim Foundation, 1969 February 28 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Gwerder, Urban to Whalen, 1969 April 11 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Hadley, Drummond and Diana to Whalen, 1968 November (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Hall, Donald to Whalen, 1971 August-September (3 letters) (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Harcourt, Brace and World, Inc.,1968-1970 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    (regarding publication of On Bear's Head)
  - Harvey, Nick (Glibe Urban Center), 1970 May-November (4 letters and 1 carbon reply) (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Haselwood, Dave to Whalen, 1966 May and 1967 May (3 letters) (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Helmsley, Kris to Whalen, 1972 February 14 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Hollo, Anselm to Whalen, 1971 October-1973 (3 letters) (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Hoogstraten, Harry to Whalen,undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Hoppe, Art to Whalen and Joan Armstrong, 1965 March (2 letters) (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Howard, Peter to Whalen, 1968-1970 (5 letters) (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Hoyem, Andrew to Whalen, 1968 November 8 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Humphrey, James to Whalen, 1969-1970 (4 letters) (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Inada, Lawson Fusai to Whalen, 1970 (2 letters) (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Kanaseki, Hisao to Whalen, 1968 November (2 letters) (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Karhu, Clif to Whalen, 1968 August (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Kelly, Robert to Whalen, 1971 August 5 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Kennedy, Dick to Whalen,1966-1968 (6 letters) (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Kerouac, Gabrielle-Ange Levesque to Whalen, 1965 December 17 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Kerouac, Jack to Whalen, 1969 January 16 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Keyes, Roger to Whalen, 1968 August 1 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Kherdian, David to Whalen, 1966-1970 (19 letters) (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Kleinzahler, August to Whalen, undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Knight, Arthur and Glee to Whalen,1973-1974, (5 letters with enclosures) (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Knox, Hugh to Whalen, 1969 March 27 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Koch, Kenneth to Whalen, 1967 October 10 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Koller, James to Whalen
    - 1965-1968 (23 letters) (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 1969-1974 (24 letters) (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Kuhn, Donald (Glide Urban Center), 1970 November (2 letters) (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Kuroda, Yoshiyuki to Whalen, 1968 December 25 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Kyger, Joanne Elizabeth to Whalen, 1966 March 28 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Kyger, Joanne Elizabeth and John P. Boyce to Whalen, 1966 May-1968 September (22 letters) (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Kyger, Joanne to Whalen, 1968 October-1971 March (21 letters) (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Le Pellec, Yves to Whalen, 1974 (2 letters) (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Linenthal, Mark to Whalen, 1968 February 6 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Lloyd, Norman to Whalen, 1968 October 2 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Loewinsohn, Ron to Whalen,1966-1968 (3 letters) (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Longville, Tim to Whalen,1969-1972 (5 letters) (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Lourie, Ivan to Whalen, 1969 September 10 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Lowell, Jim to Whalen, 1965 March-April (2 letters) (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - LaVigne, Robert to Whalen, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Leavitt, Dick to Whalen,1968-1969 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Luckenbach, Roger to Whalen, 1968 November 23 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - MacAdams, Lewis to Whalen, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - McBean, Judy to Whalen,undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - McClure, Michael to Whalen
    - 1969-1973 andundated (15 letters) (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - 1975-1977 (8 letters) (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - McCullough, Frances (Coward-McCann, Inc.) to Whalen, 1970 August 13 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - McMenamin, Thomas John to Whalen, 1969 Spring (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Madsen, Jack to Whalen, 1968 andundated (4 letters) (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Malamut, Laura to Whalen, 1968 September 21 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Malley, Joan to Whalen, 1969 July 26 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Marlowe, Alan to Whalen,1966-1968 and undated, (5 letters) (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Martin, John to Whalen
    - 1970-1971, (12 letters) (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - 1972, (10 letters) (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Sister Mary Norbert to Whalen, 1968 February 9 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Mayfield, Carl to Whalen, 1974 March 13 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Melanga, Gerard to Whalen,1966-1972, (3 letters) (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Meltzer to David to Whalen,1968-1970 and undated, (14 letters) (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Meredith, Lawrence to Whalen,1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Miles, Josephine to Whalen, 1969 February 16 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Montgomery, John to Whalen, 1974 February 14 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Morgan, Pete to Whalen, 1970 February 24 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Muste, Abraham John to Whalen, 1965 March 23 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Nelson, Gene to Whalen, 1965 March 20 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Newman, Julia to Whalen,1968-1971 (4 letters) (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Nims, John to Whalen,1973-1974 (2 letters) (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Nichol, Robert S., to Whalen, 1968 November 24 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    (includes "Kami: A Visit to Philip Whalen")
  - Norse, Harold to Whalen, 1974 September 12 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Oppenheimer, Joel to Whalen,1971-1973, (4 letters) (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Padgett, Ron to Whalen, 1967 February 5 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Parkinson, Thomas Francis
    - To Whalen,1962-1970, (9 letters) (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Poetry- "Eros: Poems for the City," "Homage to Monte Berico," "Thanatos: Poems on Death" (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Pearson, Norman Holmes to Whalen, 1974 January 6 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Penguin Books to Whalen, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Peterson, Don to Whalen, 1970 August 28, (2 letters- one in the form of a poem) (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Pivano, Fernanda Sottsass to Whalen,1966-1969 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Plymell, Charles to Whalen, 1968 1971 andundated, (4 letters) (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Rabin, Daniel to Whalen,undated (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Ray, David
    - 1965-1966, (2 letters) (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Poems sent to Whalen- "Homage to Ed Dorn," "An Idyll Perhaps," "Salisbury Sandwiches" (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Reed, Sweeney to Whalen, 1969 May 22 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Rexroth, Kenneth to Whalen,1966-1970 and undated, (9 letters and 10 poems) (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Reynolds, Lloyd to Whalen, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Rimer, Thomas to Whalen, 1966 and undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Robbins, Henry to Whalen, 1970 March 13 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Rose, Sandy to Whalen, September, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Rosenthal, Irving to Whalen, 1966 May-1967 November, (16 letters) (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Rossett, Barney to Whalen, 1965 March 19 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Sakaki, Nanao to Whalen,undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Sandberg, David to Whalen, 1966, (3 letters) (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Saroyan, Aram to Whalen
    - 1966-1969, (12 letters) (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - 1970-1972, (12 letters) (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Poems and an interview with Whalen (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Schuchat, Simon to Whalen,1972-1973, (2 letters) (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Senauke, Alan to Whalen,undated (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Shoemaker, Jack to Whalen,1969-1970, (5 letters) (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Silliman, Ron to Whalen, Richard Duerden, an Gary Snyder, 1969 January 6 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Snyder, Gary to Whalen
    - 1965-1966 December, (14 letters) (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - 1967 February-1970 October, (24 letters) (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - 1971 January-1974 November, (26 letters) (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Snyder, Gary
    - to Whalen, 1975 February-1979 June, (17 letters) (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Poems and Miscellany (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Stafford, Bill to Whalen, 1968 June 1 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Steinbeck, John IV to Peter Collier, 1968 August 7 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Stevens, Jean Andre to Whalen, 1974 July 20 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Taggart, John to Whalen, 1968 October-1970 March, (3 letters) (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Thomas, Bill to Whalen
    - 1966, (13 letters) (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - 1967 March-1968 December, (24 letters) (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Thomas, Jody to Whalen, 1968 October 3 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Thompson, L. to Whalen, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - United States Government Correspondence and Documents,1969-1970 andundated (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - University of California at Los Angeles to Whalen,1964-1968 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Van Aelstyn, Edward to Whalen, 1966-1968, (3 letters) (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Veitch, Tom to Whalen, 1971 March-May, (4 letters) (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Wagstaff, Christopher to Whalen, 1968 December -1969 February, (5 letters) (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Waldman, Anne to Whalen, 1969 February-1973 December, (20 letters) (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Wang, David Rafael to Whalen, 1966-1967, (2 letters and the poem "The Knack") (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Warsh, Lewis to Whalen, 1967-1969, (5 letters) (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Webb, Jon to Whalen, 1968 March 12 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Weinstein, Norman to Whalen, undated, (2 letters) (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Weishaus, Joel to Whalen, 1970 July-October, (5 letters) (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Wells, Michael to Whalen, 1968 December 27 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Whalen, Philip
    - To Thomas Clark, August 1967, (2 letters) (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - To Diane Di Prima, 1964 December-1968 January, (6 letters) (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - To Pamela Millward, 1967 August 21 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - To Edward Sanders,1963-1966, (6 letters) (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - To Mr. Winslow,undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
      (with Winslow's essay on Whalen- corrected by Whalen)
  - Wilentz, Elias S. to Whalen, 1966 October- November, (2 letters) (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Williams, Jonathan to Whalen,1967-1968, (7 letters and miscellaneous) (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Wilson, Robert to Whalen,1965-1970, (4 letters) (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Woessner, Warren to Whalen, 1973 April 15 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Worcester, Thomas K. to Whalen, 1966 February 8 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Wyatt, Bill to Whalen, 1968 June 6 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Young, Geoffrey to Whalen, 1971 January-December, (3 letters) (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous and Unsigned Correspondence (Box 9, Folder 19)
- Series II: Poems and Manuscripts,1941-1971
  - ABCDEFGHIJKL ..., 1965 September 6 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Above the Shrine, 1966 July 13 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Acaccias, 1952 September 27 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Acaccias: Rain, 1953 January 19 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Academic Sonnet, 1947 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - ACRL, 1963 January 4 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Address to a Younger Generation, 1960 September 26 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - The Admonitions, 1962 April 23 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Advent, 1949 November 19 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - After-Dinner Music, 1953 January 4 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - After my zero allnight vigil ... 1958 August 27 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - After the rain I go for a walk ..., 1962 November 9 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Against One Particular Theory of Literature, 1963 July 5 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Against the Magic War: An Open Letter to Robert Duncan, 1957 July 27 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - The Album, 1957 January 25 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Aleph Sub-three Has Yet to be Discovered, 1961 May 8 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - All afternoon I hunt for lost trails, searching ..., 1962 November 6 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - All night booze horrors ..., 1963 June 24 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - All wet ..., 1961 June 17 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Alone…, 1957 March 17 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Aluminum Eye. A Sentimental Recollection, 1966 February 1 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - America!, 1965 July 25 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Anchor Steam Beer, for Michael McClure, 1957 February 9 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Animal crackers in my soup ... (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Another, to the Same Lady, 1962 March 31 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - An anthology of French poetry ..., 1963 October 13 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Apedeath, 1957 February 11 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Apostrophe to a Borrowed Tiger, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Applegravy, 1962 November 23 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - April fool, April fool ..., 1941 April 3 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - April Showers Bring Rain?, 1965 April 7 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Archives of the Circuit Court of Oregon ..., 1959 January 29 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Art & Music, 1965 April 5 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Art & Society, 1962 July 24 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - The Art of Literature, 1962 October (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - As if I had turned over while sleeping ..., 1959 April 20 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - As Last Sighted, 1943 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - At any waking moment I expect ..., 1943 (Box 10, Folder 3)